<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data on Being Mas</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/data/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data on Being Mas</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>All rights reserved - 2015</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2015 15:13:32 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/data/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Pennsylvania&#39;s Steepest Race</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/SteepestRacePA/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2015 15:13:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/SteepestRacePA/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-spark-of-the-project:e821d7f6a85bcd0c723ada71edb79d57&#34;&gt;The Spark of the Project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, I went on a run with the North Park Trail Runners,
and a discussion came up about different races people signed up for.
It inevitably led to a conversation about how tough each race is.
Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong, if you are doing a race, it will be challenging
no matter what - if it&amp;rsquo;s flat, you&amp;rsquo;re probably pushing your body to
go real fast; if it&amp;rsquo;s a little hilly, maybe you&amp;rsquo;re sprinting up all
the hills; or if it&amp;rsquo;s very steep, you&amp;rsquo;ll be walking up the climbs and
running down the hills or trotting (and even the downhill can be
challenging based on the terrain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while there is no one true metric to answer the question
of &amp;ldquo;what is the most challenging race?&amp;rdquo;,
I have attempted to answer a piece of that puzzle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-races-with-hills:e821d7f6a85bcd0c723ada71edb79d57&#34;&gt;The Races With Hills&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a hill - get over it!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my time here in Pennsylvania, I&amp;rsquo;ve heard the names of different
races thrown around - Rothrock Challenge, Megatransect, Lost Turkey, etc.
I tried going through some of those races and quantifying the vertical gain per mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tricky thing here is that not every race advertises its
estimated elevation gain, and even if it does, you can&amp;rsquo;t always
trust it (I&amp;rsquo;m looking at you Rock&amp;rsquo;N The Knob). You also can&amp;rsquo;t trust the
advertised miles - actually, nor the ruuners&amp;hellip; well,
especially the runners that like to challenge themselves and
add extra off-course miles (I do this quite often&amp;hellip; some people call it getting lost).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put together a small list of &amp;ldquo;challening&amp;rdquo; races
and pulled out their elevation gain in feet and divided
it by the total miles of the race, based on data recorded from racers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far the races are as follows (in alphabetical order):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Call of the Wilds Marathon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eastern States 100&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hyner View Challenge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laurel Highlands Ultra&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Megatransect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rock&amp;rsquo;N the Knob&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rothrock Challenge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully I can update/add to this list as I do more research and get more suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;results:e821d7f6a85bcd0c723ada71edb79d57&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/SteepPA/SteepestPARace.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Graph of vertical gain (ft) per mile&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By purely looking at numbers, the Wilds Marathon has the most vertical gain per mile at 258 ft/mile,
with the Hyner View Challenge (50K) coming in closely behind it at 256 ft/mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below you can see for yourself, all the numbers that went into the graph above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/SteepPA/RaceData.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Race data&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data:e821d7f6a85bcd0c723ada71edb79d57&#34;&gt;Data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the crux of what I&amp;rsquo;m saying relies on data that I put together,
I think it is worthwhile noting where it came from. I tried to gather
together blog race reports and the numbers that people reported there,
but I was also able to track down some data from publicly available sources (i.e. Strava).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be thorough with my results, I tried using a decent sample size to
get an average worth reporting since I know the way GPS works varies
between watches and the different algorithms companies utilize.
Decent sample size meant 4 or more people (not that many, I know,
but finding the data was hard).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;distance:e821d7f6a85bcd0c723ada71edb79d57&#34;&gt;Distance&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distance category for the race should be obvious,
that&amp;rsquo;s where you know the distance you&amp;rsquo;re signing up for&amp;hellip;
roughly. In reality you&amp;rsquo;re the Eastern States, it may depend
on how lost you get, whereas the Rothrock Challenge, it might
be an extra challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, the quoted distance is what was obtained.
All races cannot guarantee you&amp;rsquo;ll run the exact amount, and it
may depend on the course you take. The one interesting result
was the Laurel Highlands coming in about 3 miles short. I haven&amp;rsquo;t
run the race, so I&amp;rsquo;m not sure where the discrepancy would come in.
Potentially, the uphill + downhill gains could make up the 3 miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;elevation:e821d7f6a85bcd0c723ada71edb79d57&#34;&gt;Elevation&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the main data that I used for my thoughts here.
Elevation is a tricky thing. I won&amp;rsquo;t go into the details, but
&lt;a href=&#34;http://regex.info/blog/2015-05-09/2568&#34;&gt;Jeff Friedl&lt;/a&gt; blogged about
how Strava may inflate their elevation numbers. It&amp;rsquo;s very difficult to
tell, and quite honestly, I used Strava for 95% of what I did here,
so at least they&amp;rsquo;re all consistently inflated (hopefully).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, again, used the same method of just pulling different
racer&amp;rsquo;s GPS Elevation gain data and then averaged at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-thoughts:e821d7f6a85bcd0c723ada71edb79d57&#34;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this mean that the Wilds Marathon is the toughest race in PA?
Heck no! The distance of the Eastern States add a whole new element
of pain to the table. But then you have Rothrock and Megatransect
that both add a layer of complexity with the amount of rocks and
technical portions that also make it challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of trail running is each race offers its own set of
challenges. I think the lesson to learn here is you may need to try
each one to determine which is the most challenging for yourself!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>