<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Design on Being Mas</title>
    <link>http://tcastillo.me/tags/design/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Design on Being Mas</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>All rights reserved - 2015</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 May 2015 18:09:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://tcastillo.me/tags/design/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Blogging With Hugo</title>
      <link>http://tcastillo.me/post/BloggingWithHugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2015 18:09:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://tcastillo.me/post/BloggingWithHugo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;hello-world:837b790d0077db53636026f3d2aee5f3&#34;&gt;Hello World&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have finally decided to do something with this website of mine.
For a while it&amp;rsquo;s been sitting here with a static page on top, but with some spare time
and a bit of desire for a challenge, I have updated the site. The goal will be to
continue to blog on it, while adding additional content to the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main focus will be some of my random adventures in life, but at the same time I&amp;rsquo;ll
be blogging from time to time about my trials of maintaining this site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I built the site using &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; and picked up a theme called
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vjeantet/hugo-theme-casper&#34;&gt;Casper&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s a little tricky
since I&amp;rsquo;m going about the blog in an odd fashion. First I edit files on my computer
at work/home/phone. Then I use git to push the content to github. Then, when I get
a chance, I&amp;rsquo;ll use git to pull the changed content on my VPS with Digital Ocean. Once there,
I use Hugo to generate the static pages for the content, which is then copied
to a separate location which is where NGINX picks up the content and puts it
on the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-Steps&#34;&gt;hugo new -t casper post/BloggingWithHugo.md
** Write blog post in notepad **

git push https://github.com/elShambler/beingMas_blog

** Log in to VPS **
git pull
hugo -t casper
cp -r public/* &amp;lt;/location/for/nginx/host&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Convoluted and most likely unnecessary. Because this is my first real experience with
maintaing a webserver, it is a constant learning process. With any luck, I will have
greater efficiency in the future. For now, this method will have to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next thing to try is symlinks and/or rsync to just copy the files directly for nginx
to serve.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>