<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Being Mas</title>
    <link>https://tcastillo.me/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Being Mas</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>All rights reserved - 2015</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 May 2016 15:02:20 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://tcastillo.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Hyner - A Humble Race</title>
      <link>https://tcastillo.me/post/Hyner-Humble-Race/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2016 15:02:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tcastillo.me/post/Hyner-Humble-Race/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tcastillo.me/images/Hyner2016/Hyner_AdamAndClayton-01.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;No. 2 and No. 4 Atop Humble Hill&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my two years living in Pennsylvania, I&amp;rsquo;ve come to understand just how
beautiful Pennsylvania is. Truly, there are many different ways to
experience the natural wonders of the state. However, in central PA, the
trails are rugged and hills are steep and relentless, traveling by foot
is the best way to explore the wilds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hikerun.com&#34;&gt;Hyner Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; showcases some of the best
parts of PA while is simultaneously grueling and unforgiving - whether
you&amp;rsquo;re challenging yourself with the 25 km or 50 km. It traverses
through the winding creeks and ridge sides of Hyner View State park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tcastillo.me/images/Hyner2016/Hyner_hangGlideTakeoff.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Hyner View&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the 50k race boasts upwards of 7500 feet of elevation gain, the
25k is no joke either, as it climbs 3 of the same &amp;ldquo;hills&amp;rdquo; as the 50k
giving it over 4500 feet of elevation gain. Over both of those
distances, you&amp;rsquo;ll find yourself in a beautiful and remote part of the
park and state, and often times questioning why you thought this
challenge was a good idea to begin with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-hyner-why-50k:264e03aa8d6ea86b3f80d7d78d6fed0e&#34;&gt;Why Hyner? Why 50k?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race has been going on since 2007, but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until 2008 that the
25k course was established to what it is today. In 2012, there were
enough crazy people to offer a 50k variant. Last year was really my
first foray into the Pennsylvania trail running scene, and the first
race I did was the Hyner 25k and was hooked. This year I got to do the
50k. I may do a separate post for a race report, but here is a quick
summary - a perfect blend of beauty, steep climbs, and runnable single
track - &lt;sup&gt;10&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt; would recommend to a friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe a lot of people got my recommendation, as I was quite surprised by
the number of people that turned up for the 50k this year. Although, I
will say, the number of people in the 25k last year was shocking to me
as well; the sign of a good race. With the increase in number of
entrants, my competitive mind began to wonder if there was an increase
in the amount of talent that was present as well. But if there was, how
much? Was this year faster overall? And why were there so many fast
people here??&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of factors probably went in to its increase in popularity: the
overall trend of the popularity of the sport for both sub-ultra and
ultra distances; the 25k and 50k are both part of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trailrunnermag.com/races/trophy-series&#34;&gt;Trail Runner Magazine&amp;rsquo;s Trophy Series&lt;/a&gt;,
for the second year in a row; the 25k is part of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mountaincup.com/schedule&#34;&gt;La Sportiva Mountain Cup&lt;/a&gt;;
and the 50k is part of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://patriplecrown.com/&#34;&gt;Pennsylvania Triple Crown of Mountain Running&lt;/a&gt;.
So there&amp;rsquo;s a lot going on here!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I could go in to detail about the 25k, I&amp;rsquo;ll touch on it briefly,
but my curiousity lies with the 50k&amp;hellip; partly because that is the race I
participated in, but also because the ultra distance is still a newer
category but quickly gaining in popularity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;everyone-likes-a-challenge:264e03aa8d6ea86b3f80d7d78d6fed0e&#34;&gt;Everyone Likes A Challenge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to when the first 50k was offered, there were initially 99 entrants
in the race. Now there are 258. My how the times have changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tcastillo.me/images/Hyner2016/Race%20Participants-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Race Participants&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might notice that in 2015, the 25k has the most participants and
decreased in 2016 - this is due to the increased interest in the 50k.
There are rules that allow for a certain number of people to be
out on the course at one time. Because of the rising popularity of the
50k, the number of entrants allowed to the 25k was cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past year, 2016 saw the most challengers on the 50k course and an
increase from 155 people to 258 from last year to this year.
So with the added number of legs and competition on the course,
how does this change the speed of the finishers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;getting-faster:264e03aa8d6ea86b3f80d7d78d6fed0e&#34;&gt;Getting Faster&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, as you may have guessed, the field got faster - well at least the
competition at the top did. While the 25k brings in some top notch
talent, the overall pace of that race category is slower than than 50k.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tcastillo.me/images/Hyner2016/Speed%20Comparison-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Speed Comparison&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This happens simply because there are runners and hikers taking on the
25k, while the 50k is reserved for anyone that has met the time
constraints on a qualifying race. So there&amp;rsquo;s a selective process for
those attempting the 50k where hikers are filtered out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean the 25k is just a frolick in the woods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you then look at how the top finisher&amp;rsquo;s times have increased over the
years - you can get a sense for how the speed has been growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tcastillo.me/images/Hyner2016/Hyner_MattLipsey.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;No. 1 in 25k - Matt Lipsey&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, you&amp;rsquo;ll notice that the average times for the 25k actually went up
from the previous year. &lt;a href=&#34;http://matthiaslipshitz.blogspot.com/2016/04/hyner-worth-view.html&#34;&gt;Matt Lipsey commented on how that year felt slow&lt;/a&gt;,
and it was certainly reflected in finishing times. Otherwise, with the
increase in participants to the 50k, the finishers times got way faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tcastillo.me/images/Hyner2016/Top%2010%20Pace-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Top 10 Average Pace&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this because the race is growing in size, so the number of fast
people entering is increasing? Or maybe the same people are putting in
more training and more rigorous training to be faster than last year?
Probably a combination of both. But you can definitely see how the depth
of the field is increasing as well. By that, I mean, the number of
people clustered around the same times and how easy it is to jump ranks
based on a faster finish time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, the standard deviation. I left this part out, but the
competition has certainly become tighter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you can see overall times and just how fast the 50k has become -
below shows the top 25 finisher&amp;rsquo;s times (not pace). Simply astounding
how fast this race has become. Makes you wonder what it will look like
next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tcastillo.me/images/Hyner2016/50k%20Finish%20Times-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;50k Finish Times&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;opt-outside:264e03aa8d6ea86b3f80d7d78d6fed0e&#34;&gt;Opt Outside&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tcastillo.me/images/Hyner2016/Hyner_alongWall.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Along the Hyner Lookout&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s just people wanting to be more active, or more people
wanting to challenge themselves, or just wanting to get
outside - something is definitely happening to the Pennsylvania trail
racing scene, and for the better. With the added incentives this year of
the 25k and 50k variants, along with people striving to best their own
times from previous years, the growing number of people is sure to bring
in a growing number of talented legs as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to being able to see what the rest of the year brings and
how the newer races fare. With Worlds End 100k in only its second year,
and Eastern States 100 in its third, there&amp;rsquo;s bound to be more top racers
emerging from the technical, gritty, and rooty trails that this state
has to offer. Best to get out there and keep running!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1st photo is credit to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/mikemcneil/albums&#34;&gt;Mike McNeil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Remainder of photos are credited to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.momentumphotography.net/#featured-athlete&#34;&gt;Momentum Photography&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Rut 2014 - Race Report</title>
      <link>https://tcastillo.me/post/2014-Rut_Race-Report/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2015 10:09:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tcastillo.me/post/2014-Rut_Race-Report/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-year-anniversary:7f89b66f2dfb35eb5d4774d8834292c1&#34;&gt;1-Year Anniversary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This weekend (09/05/2015) is the 2015 Rut in Big Sky, Montana. That means it&amp;rsquo;s been
one year since I had the opportunity to race there. I never got around to
writing a race report and decided this would be the best time to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;overview:7f89b66f2dfb35eb5d4774d8834292c1&#34;&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rut is becoming a very popular race as it is one of the few true sky/mountain races
in the USA. It is featured in the SkyRunner World Series, along with the USA Series.
Last year (when I ran it) it featured top male and female athletes such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/K%C3%ADlian_Jornet_Burgada&#34;&gt;Kilian Jornet&lt;/a&gt;
, &lt;a href=&#34;http://sagecanaday.com/athlete/&#34;&gt;Sage Canaday&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://running.competitor.com/2014/07/trail-running/runner-struck-lightning-keeps-running_107955&#34;&gt;Adam Campbell&lt;/a&gt;
 (among others), and for the females: Emelie Forsberg, Kasie Enman, and Anna &amp;ldquo;Frosty&amp;rdquo; Frost.
 The race director is Mike Foote (who got 2nd this year at Hardrock 100, behind Kilian) and put together quite an
epic course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;backstory:7f89b66f2dfb35eb5d4774d8834292c1&#34;&gt;Backstory&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May of 2014, I moved to Pittsburgh, PA from Houston, TX. Not going to lie, I had a challenging time with the transition and saying goodbye to my home, family, and friends.
In an attempt to find fulfillment in my new city and home, I decided to focus on running - trail running. With this new mindset, I figured I should start reading
about it too - so I picked up an issue of Trail Runner Magazine to begin this new hobby of mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magazine has a section called &amp;ldquo;Featured Races&amp;rdquo; and this particular article had one titled &lt;a href=&#34;http://trailrunnermag.com/races/15-featured-races/1466-the-rut-50k&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Rut 50k&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.
I read it, thought it sounded epic, and decided right then and there to look it up on my computer. Sure enough, it was sold out&amp;hellip; but they were accepting names
into their waiting list. My thought process was something like - &amp;ldquo;If I sign up, maybe it&amp;rsquo;ll give me motivation to train for it next year when I actually get in.&amp;rdquo; So I signed up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I started running more on the trails, I was also nursing a knee injury that the doctors told me I needed surgery for. I actually went as far as scheduling the surgery. However,
after running more on the trails, and doing cross-training with picking up crossfit, my knee actually started feeling better. I canceled the surgery. This came with a bit of a cost, since I was being tender with my knee, I was not running very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;training:7f89b66f2dfb35eb5d4774d8834292c1&#34;&gt;Training&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tcastillo.me/images/2014Rut/EmailConfirmation.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;I made it off the wait list!&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In early August (6th of August), I got an email that said I made it in! I was shocked. The race was September 13th meaning I now had to go from running like 10 miles a week to
running 31 miles up a mountain in one day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I had done a 50k in Texas and considered myself a decent runner/athlete prior to moving to Pittsburgh, I soon realized there was one aspect that I was very new to - hills.
Houston has no hills, and I quickly learned that running on the trails where there is elevation change IS NOT the same as running on flat ground. I made sure that my training took
into account many hills and long distances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I learned a lot in those 6 weeks I had to train: I learned how to run on rocky terrain (kind of); I got better at running on a treadmill for long periods of time since a
bachelor party to Las Vegas left me with one option for getting hill work in; and I pushed myself to go long distance by myself and self-sustained. Come September 13th, I was
ready&amp;hellip; or at least as ready as I could&amp;rsquo;ve been with really only 6 weeks of training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pre-race:7f89b66f2dfb35eb5d4774d8834292c1&#34;&gt;Pre-Race&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tcastillo.me/images/2014Rut/AirportView.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Airport view of Bozeman Mountains&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I flew in to Bozeman Montana all hyped up and ready to take on the challenge of the race. In order to acclimatize to the altitude better, I flew in 12 hours before the race (&lt;em&gt;joke&lt;/em&gt;).
It actually worked out really well because my college roommate (3 out of 4 years) lived in Bozeman, so I was grateful that I got to spend time with the great Danny Z. He helped me out a ton with giving me a place to stay, and a car to drive, along with just being able to catch up with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was driving towards Big Sky for the pre-race check in, I realized it was too late - I couldn&amp;rsquo;t abandon ship now&amp;hellip; I had already paid my entry fee, paid for a flight (I was in Montana!), and what&amp;rsquo;s worse is I told
DZ and his friends that I would be running the race, so backing out would seem pretty lame. The issue was - Lone Peak (THE mountain at Big Sky) is a &lt;strong&gt;BIG&lt;/strong&gt; mountain, and at
11,166 ft, I was beginning to question whether I had really thought this out and trained properly. Oh well, no turning back now; luckily, the atmosphere was quite energetic and I was mesmerized
in the fact that I actually made it and was about to embark on an extremely challenging but amazing adventure!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;race-day:7f89b66f2dfb35eb5d4774d8834292c1&#34;&gt;Race Day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I approached the staging area for the resort in the darkness of the morning, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help but think how this seems to be starting a new chapter to my life - here I am at a race where
I don&amp;rsquo;t know anyone, it&amp;rsquo;s a distance that I&amp;rsquo;ve done before but I&amp;rsquo;ll be climbing a mountain, and all in, it&amp;rsquo;ll be epic if I finish. I was pumped! The temperature in the morning was
a cool 38 *F but slated to rise up to 60 *F with clear skies - perfect racing weather. I had my backpack filled with food, water, and room for a jacket once it warmed up, but no room for feeling sorry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race started in 3 waves - crazy, mostly crazy, and average crazy. I think I picked the intermediate group just because I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to wait any longer. We started in the dark and
immediately started climbing upwards. I was quite shocked at the fact that we were walking right at the start - wasn&amp;rsquo;t this a race? Why aren&amp;rsquo;t we running? So I tried running
up the hill to pass people&amp;hellip; I quickly found out why we were walking. My legs started burning and I was moving at roughly the same speed as the walkers, but sucking 2x the
amount of air. Walking it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I figured that lesson out, the race became a little more manageable. I ran when I could, walked fast on the uphills. I tried running the downhills quickly, but was no match
for the more experienced runners. I watched their technique as they seemed to glide over rocky downhill terrain that looked like it could roll a few ankles. I tried to keep at my
own pace and not focus too much on the fact that I was being passed a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t remember at what point along the race this was, but I started to feel my body get more and more tired exponentially faster than I had recalled on previous runs. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t really
figure it out, but kept going. At a certain point, we got to a rocky trail that started to lead directly upward. It was then it hit me - we were now at some sort of treeline where
the terrain was all rocks and no vegetation and the elevation is much higher than I was used to. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure I had such a clear thought at the time, but what crossed my mind
was probably like, &amp;ldquo;Wow! We&amp;rsquo;re high&amp;rdquo;. Either way, the elevation was getting to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;climbing-up-to-headwaters-ridge:7f89b66f2dfb35eb5d4774d8834292c1&#34;&gt;Climbing up to Headwaters Ridge&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/aBO8IFbnp5E&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This portion of the race really blew my mind as it was just completely different than anything I could&amp;rsquo;ve expected to run. I don&amp;rsquo;t remember the name of this section, and I&amp;rsquo;m sure
other race reports out there may have a more detailed description of this, but this marked the first real big climb. I believe it was around mile 12 climbing up to one of the summits.
The course was on a scree and boulder field that had maybe a 15% grade to it (after checking Sage Canaday&amp;rsquo;s race report, he says it hit 46% grade!). The climb continued upward for what seemed like a mile or two. But at a certain point, it switched from
being a big open field, to a scree/dirt ridgeline. I wish I could&amp;rsquo;ve gotten video of how precarious this ledge seemed, but I was focused on not slipping, and nothing else was
really crossing my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tcastillo.me/images/2014Rut/HeadwatersDescent.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Descent from Headwaters Ridge&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The climb continued and I made it to the top of this first real big climb. I felt very much out of gas. I saw another guy at the top with some paramedics because he was having trouble
catching his breath, and was thankful that the altitude didn&amp;rsquo;t affect me as bad, but knew very well that could&amp;rsquo;ve been me. Back down the mountain we went, with the knowledge that we
still had to summit Lone Peak at mile 20. A highlight along this portion was on the route down, there was a guy that was kind of just running at an easy pace but seemingly talking to
himself. Then as myself and others listened in, it appeared he was on his phone! He was just talking with his wife back home.. crazy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;swiftcurrent-and-the-summit:7f89b66f2dfb35eb5d4774d8834292c1&#34;&gt;Swiftcurrent and the Summit&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tcastillo.me/images/2014Rut/SummitAscent.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Climb up to Lone Peak&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll fast forward and I made it to the &amp;ldquo;Swiftcurrent&amp;rdquo; aid station, which is about 18.5 miles in and maybe 70% of the climbing done. It was there that I really started to feel extremely
tired. The path up to the Swiftcurrent aid station made a switch from rocky single track to rocky fire road and was just a steady climb up to the tram station. I finally made it up, but
started to notice that I was pushing the tail end of the cut-offs for each of the aid stations. When I arrived at Swiftcurrent, I then had 2 hours to climb the 1.5 miles up to Lone
Peak. Under normal circumstances, that is laughable that I would question it. But when there&amp;rsquo;s just over 2000&amp;rsquo; to climb in that distance, the challenge is significantly greater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you&amp;rsquo;ll hear runners say, &amp;ldquo;Run 5 minutes, walk 2 minutes&amp;rdquo; or something like that. At this portion of the &amp;ldquo;race&amp;rdquo;, I was under the schedule of &amp;ldquo;walk 10 steps, take a 1 minute break&amp;rdquo;.
I started pacing back and forth with a guy from Chicago who was doing the same thing. We were both struggling pretty bad. I tried not to take too many breaks as I was mindful of the
cutoff time coming up quickly on me, but my legs had trouble keeping up with me here. However, I made it to the top, with about 10 minutes to spare before the cutoff!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tcastillo.me/images/2014Rut/PhotoAtTop.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Summit Photo&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was seriously contemplating calling it a day at that point. I was not looking forward to climbing back down since my knees were killing me and the jagged rocks and steep
grade only made it harder to go down. After refueling and talking with someone at the aid station (and grabbing a sweet photo), I just kept going. I had 6 miles to cover and
about 4 hours to make the next cutoff at the Andesite cutoff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;trekking-to-andesite:7f89b66f2dfb35eb5d4774d8834292c1&#34;&gt;Trekking to Andesite&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, the climb off of Lone Peak was more painful than I had though it could&amp;rsquo;ve been. My knees were swollen to what seemed like twice their size, and my ankles felt
like I put them through a whack-a-mole competition, where the whackers were padded with rocks. Anyway, I finally made it down but wasn&amp;rsquo;t really being passed by anyone, which
likely meant I was one of the last competitors, and I surely wasn&amp;rsquo;t going fast enough to pass anyone. My knees weren&amp;rsquo;t getting any better, and my body felt like it was
ready to give up. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t quite sure on what my time or distance was since my watch had died around mile 5 (perfect timing, right?), but I was pretty certain I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going
to be able to make it. I kept hiking and running when I could, but I eventually resolved in my head that I will just show up at Andesite and catch a ride down since my legs
had had enough. For me, this was the end, my DNF-march. I just had to make it to Andesite to make it official.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as I had come to this unfortunate decision, a runner came up behind me. It was a woman that seemed to be going at a good pace. I was surprised because I didn&amp;rsquo;t understand
how someone going so fast could be this far back. Well it turned out she was doing a rover&amp;rsquo;s job and picking up the last people on the race course. She stayed with me for a while
and we chatted. She asked where I was from and what brought me to this race. I told her I read about it in a magazine - Trail Runner. Well I was in for a surprise - she was the
author! I was quite surprised since here she is now picking me up as a straggler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we ran a little bit more, she informed me there was one person behind me, I had about 2.5 miles to cover in an hour and said as she departed, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ll see you at the finish!&amp;rdquo;
So there it was, I had my goal in front of me. I pushed through the pain and picked up my pace and was more or less hobbling down the course on my sore knees. I passed two guys that
had passed me a long time ago, that seemed pretty confident with their pace and were just cruising along. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t so sure they would make it, but I pushed a little faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cursed a little bit as I clabmored up through the downhill mountain bike course (note: runners are going up where the mountain bikers typically down). I was hoping that would be
the last of the uphill. Once back on a fire road, I saw the last aid station, and they saw me. They were surprised at the sight of me and yelled as I was approaching that I had 3
minutes! They were whistling and jingling their cowbell - everything I needed to get me excited to finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was SO rejuvenated to have another life and a chance at actually finishing! This aid station was at 26.5 miles, meaning I had about 5 miles to the finish, and mostly all downhill.
I just couldn&amp;rsquo;t believe it. They radioed in to Mike Foote that the last racer was leaving their aid station as they closed down their station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-finish:7f89b66f2dfb35eb5d4774d8834292c1&#34;&gt;The Finish&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tcastillo.me/images/2014Rut/FinalRun.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Final portion of the run&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last portion of the trail was very much what you see in the picture. Very runnable and slightly downhill. There were portions that took us back through the woods, but for the most
part, it was what you&amp;rsquo;d expect from a trail run (as opposed to the previous 26 miles that was mostly mountain trails). While my knees were bothering me a lot at this point, I was
able to keep a steady pace. I got a little upset when there was a set of climbs in the final mile. I think they just put the hills there to add insult to injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could hear the loudspeaker as I was approaching, and felt my heart beat faster and faster. As I turned a corner out of the woods, I saw the finish line and didn&amp;rsquo;t slow down. I heard
them call out the last racer was approaching, and I got a lot of cheers as I crossed the finish line as the final racer! I got a nice greeting from Mike Foote and got awarded my finishers
&amp;ldquo;medal&amp;rdquo; (it&amp;rsquo;s a piece of elk hide). I did it! I finished the race, and was as proud as ever!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After celebrating a little at the resort and getting some food, and texting Danny and my mom that I was, in fact, alive, I drove on back to Bozeman. I ended a great day with a great night
celebrating with friends! I had a little trouble going up the stairs, but for the most part, was all in one piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-thoughts:7f89b66f2dfb35eb5d4774d8834292c1&#34;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One year later, I look back at that race as still one of my proudest and toughest accomplishments. I had such a strong resolve to quit the race and feel sorry for myself, as I had plenty
of good excuses - but the Trail Runner author Rachel Toor really gave me the push I needed (after getting me into the race in the first place), and I dug deep
and was able to finish. I&amp;rsquo;ll take a last place finish over DNF anytime. I was indeed extremely grateful for the opportunity to run the race. I didn&amp;rsquo;t get a chance to go back this
past year, but hopefully can improve my finish next time I make it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven&amp;rsquo;t had enough to see yet, check this video out - produced by the makers of the Rut. &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/dQoS--WFRzI&#34;&gt;Experience the Rut - Episode 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pennsylvania&#39;s Steepest Race</title>
      <link>https://tcastillo.me/post/SteepestRacePA/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2015 15:13:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tcastillo.me/post/SteepestRacePA/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-spark-of-the-project:e821d7f6a85bcd0c723ada71edb79d57&#34;&gt;The Spark of the Project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, I went on a run with the North Park Trail Runners,
and a discussion came up about different races people signed up for.
It inevitably led to a conversation about how tough each race is.
Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong, if you are doing a race, it will be challenging
no matter what - if it&amp;rsquo;s flat, you&amp;rsquo;re probably pushing your body to
go real fast; if it&amp;rsquo;s a little hilly, maybe you&amp;rsquo;re sprinting up all
the hills; or if it&amp;rsquo;s very steep, you&amp;rsquo;ll be walking up the climbs and
running down the hills or trotting (and even the downhill can be
challenging based on the terrain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while there is no one true metric to answer the question
of &amp;ldquo;what is the most challenging race?&amp;rdquo;,
I have attempted to answer a piece of that puzzle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-races-with-hills:e821d7f6a85bcd0c723ada71edb79d57&#34;&gt;The Races With Hills&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a hill - get over it!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my time here in Pennsylvania, I&amp;rsquo;ve heard the names of different
races thrown around - Rothrock Challenge, Megatransect, Lost Turkey, etc.
I tried going through some of those races and quantifying the vertical gain per mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tricky thing here is that not every race advertises its
estimated elevation gain, and even if it does, you can&amp;rsquo;t always
trust it. You also can&amp;rsquo;t trust the advertised miles - actually, nor the ruuners&amp;hellip; well,
especially the runners that like to challenge themselves and
add extra off-course miles (I do this quite often&amp;hellip; some people call it getting lost).
To assist with accuracy, I gathered together GPS data for the different races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put together a small list of &amp;ldquo;challening&amp;rdquo; races
and pulled out their elevation gain in feet and divided
it by the total miles of the race, based on data recorded from racers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far the races are as follows (in alphabetical order):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Call of the Wilds Marathon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eastern States 100&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hyner View Challenge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laurel Highlands Ultra&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Megatransect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rock&amp;rsquo;N the Knob&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rothrock Challenge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frozen Snot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Laurel Highlands (50K)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Worlds End Ultra&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Worlds End Ultra (50K)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dirty Kiln Half Marathon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Glacier Ridge Trail Ultra&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Glacier Ridge Trail Ultra (50k)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hell Hath No Hurry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hell Hath No Hurry (50k)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully I can update/add to this list as I do more research and get more suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;results:e821d7f6a85bcd0c723ada71edb79d57&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Categorizing the races by their elevation gain/mile only reveals one degree of difficulty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tcastillo.me/images/SteepPA/SteepestPARace.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Graph of vertical gain (ft) per mile&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By purely looking at numbers, the Frozen Snot is by far the steepest race with 389 ft/mile.
What makes that race even more of a challenge is the fact that it&amp;rsquo;s held at the end of
January. Aside from that, the Wilds Marathon has the second most vertical gain per mile at 258 ft/mile,
with the Hyner View Challenge (50K) coming in closely behind it at 256 ft/mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below you can see for yourself, all the numbers that went into the graph above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tcastillo.me/images/SteepPA/RaceData.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Race data&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to add in the Pittsburgh Marathon for reference on how a &amp;ldquo;hilly&amp;rdquo; road race compares.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-with-interactive-graph:e821d7f6a85bcd0c723ada71edb79d57&#34;&gt;Update with Interactive Graph&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put this data into a CSV file and used a webservice called &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly&#34;&gt;Plotly&lt;/a&gt; to
style the data a little differently than excel was letting me and add comprehension to the races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See below:
&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;https://plot.ly/~elShambler/244/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; title=&#34;PA Races - Races by pace and Elevation gain/mile&#34; style=&#34;display: block; text-align: center;&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://plot.ly/~elShambler/244.png&#34; alt=&#34;PA Races - Races by pace and Elevation gain/mile&#34; style=&#34;max-width: 100%;width: 1598px;&#34;  width=&#34;1598&#34; onerror=&#34;this.onerror=null;this.src=&#39;https://plot.ly/404.png&#39;;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;script data-plotly=&#34;elShambler:244&#34;  src=&#34;https://plot.ly/embed.js&#34; async&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have added some additional data that I used to make this plot - pace. I grabbed an average of
the top 10 finishers&amp;rsquo; paces and used that as an additional data point to graph against. The
reasoning behind this and the above graph is to add additional character to the different
races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hope in including this data is to give an overall enlightenment to how a race
will feel when it comes time for raceday. The higher the bubble is, the slower
pace you can expect, and the darker the bubble, the more climbing there is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something kind of interesting that I have been pondering after making this graph is
if there is some sort of plateau of base pace for varying lengths of races. I know
that as the body&amp;rsquo;s metabolism switches systems over long periods of high expenditure,
the pace will drop, but wonder how it plays into elevation gain too?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data:e821d7f6a85bcd0c723ada71edb79d57&#34;&gt;Data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the crux of what I&amp;rsquo;m saying relies on data that I put together,
I think it is worthwhile noting where it came from. I tried to gather
together blog race reports and the numbers that people reported there,
but I was also able to track down some data from publicly available sources (i.e. Strava).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be thorough with my results, I tried using a decent sample size to
get an average worth reporting since I know the way GPS works varies
between watches and the different algorithms companies utilize.
Decent sample size meant 4 or more people (not that many, I know,
but finding the data was hard).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;distance:e821d7f6a85bcd0c723ada71edb79d57&#34;&gt;Distance&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distance category for the race should be obvious,
that&amp;rsquo;s where you know the distance you&amp;rsquo;re signing up for&amp;hellip;
roughly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, the reported distance is what was ran.
The data used here was the GPS recorded distance. I compiled
different racer&amp;rsquo;s data, and averaged them together. I tried to
ensure the GPS route followed the plotted course for the race,
although this was more of a rough estimate. I also tried to make
sure the distance made sense and that the runners finished the
course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All races cannot guarantee you&amp;rsquo;ll run the exact amount that was
initially advertised though, and it may depend on the
course you take (i.e. getting lost). The one interesting result
was the Laurel Highlands coming in about 3 miles short. I haven&amp;rsquo;t
run the race, so I&amp;rsquo;m not sure where the discrepancy would come in.
Potentially, the uphill + downhill gains could make up the 3 miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;elevation:e821d7f6a85bcd0c723ada71edb79d57&#34;&gt;Elevation&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elevation was the main data that I used for my thoughts here.
Elevation is a tricky thing. I won&amp;rsquo;t go into the details, but
&lt;a href=&#34;http://regex.info/blog/2015-05-09/2568&#34;&gt;Jeff Friedl&lt;/a&gt; blogged about
how Strava may inflate/overestimate their elevation numbers. It&amp;rsquo;s very difficult to
tell, and quite honestly, I used Strava for 95% of my data,
so at least they&amp;rsquo;re all consistently inflated (hopefully).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, again, used the same method of just pulling different
racer&amp;rsquo;s GPS Elevation gain data and then averaged at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-thoughts:e821d7f6a85bcd0c723ada71edb79d57&#34;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this mean that the Wilds Marathon or Frozen Snot is the toughest race in PA?
Heck no! The distance of the Eastern States add a whole new element
of pain to the table. But then you have Rothrock and Megatransect
that both add a layer of complexity with the amount of rocks and
technical portions that also make it challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Frozen Snot definitely is an interesting beast because of its
steep ascents over short distance - it approaches the climbing
difficulty of a VK (vertical kilometer race). Runnability is also
huge into the challenges of a race - this has to do with the
technicality of the course. As I said above, the body&amp;rsquo;s method
of producing energy shifts at a certain point (I don&amp;rsquo;t remember
what it is, but I want to say after maybe 8 hours of heavy
calorie expenditure?) and after that, maintaining a constant
energy output becomes even more challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this to say that no single race is quantitatively better than
another race. The beauty of trail running is each race offers its own set of
challenges. I think the lesson to learn here is you may need to try
each one to determine which is the most challenging for yourself!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ABOUT ME</title>
      <link>https://tcastillo.me/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2015 17:47:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tcastillo.me/about/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-am-i:6083a88ee3411b0d17ce02d738f69d47&#34;&gt;Who Am I?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://tcastillo.me/images/headshot.jpeg&#34; 
style=&#34;float: right; padding-left: 50px; margin-left: -120px; margin-right: 200px; width: 25%; height: 25%;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a normal guy working a normal job but try and push myself to
be more than just a desk slave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spend time running through the trails and getting a full dose of the outdoors.
I have begun running ultramarathons, but am still fairly new to the scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other areas that I dabble in (i.e. hobbies, and not a professional) include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Photography&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Woodworking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beekeeping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for checking me out!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blogging With Hugo</title>
      <link>https://tcastillo.me/post/BloggingWithHugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2015 18:09:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tcastillo.me/post/BloggingWithHugo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;hello-world:837b790d0077db53636026f3d2aee5f3&#34;&gt;Hello World&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have finally decided to do something with this website of mine.
For a while it&amp;rsquo;s been sitting here with a static page on top, but with some spare time
and a bit of desire for a challenge, I have updated the site. The goal will be to
continue to blog on it, while adding additional content to the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main focus will be some of my random adventures in life, but at the same time I&amp;rsquo;ll
be blogging from time to time about my trials of maintaining this site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I built the site using &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; and picked up a theme called
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vjeantet/hugo-theme-casper&#34;&gt;Casper&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s a little tricky
since I&amp;rsquo;m going about the blog in an odd fashion. First I edit files on my computer
at work/home/phone. Then I use git to push the content to github. Then, when I get
a chance, I&amp;rsquo;ll use git to pull the changed content on my VPS with Digital Ocean. Once there,
I use Hugo to generate the static pages for the content, which is then copied
to a separate location which is where NGINX picks up the content and puts it
on the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-Steps&#34;&gt;hugo new -t casper post/BloggingWithHugo.md
** Write blog post in notepad **

git push https://github.com/elShambler/beingMas_blog

** Log in to VPS **
git pull
hugo -t casper
cp -r public/* &amp;lt;/location/for/nginx/host&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Convoluted and most likely unnecessary. Because this is my first real experience with
maintaing a webserver, it is a constant learning process. With any luck, I will have
greater efficiency in the future. For now, this method will have to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next thing to try is symlinks and/or rsync to just copy the files directly for nginx
to serve.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>